A Guide to the Alexandria Office of Sheriff Jail Records, 1891-1948
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
Alexandria Office of Sheriff Jail Records, 1891-1948
Alexandria Library, Local History/Special Collections
54
5 boxes
Late 19th and early 20th century records from the Alexandria Sheriff's Department.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Mr. Richard R. Ruscak, Undersheriff, City of Alexandria, March 22, 2002.
Biographical/Historical Information
After 1752, the Fairfax County Court appointed a sheriff to Alexandria, and around the same time the first jail in the city was located on Market Square near the courthouse. The jail was later moved to the foot of Wolfe Street before moving again to a new building constructed around 1825 on the northeast corner of Princess and North St. Asaph Streets. The St. Asaph Street building served as the city jail for over 150 years. Deteriorating conditions led to several lawsuits, and eventually to the renovation of the old jail in 1979 and the construction of the new Alexandria Detention Center (completed in 1987).
Scope and Content
Jail Registers noting both city and state prisoners showing name of prisoner, race, felony or misdemeanor charged with, sentence, resolution of sentence, fees and fines; Commitments for Examination showing name of prisoner, felony or misdemeanor charged with, sentence, date of sentence; Court Orders showing date, name of prisoner, race, age, felony or misdemeanor charged with, sentence; Jail Service Certificates showing name of prisoner, date released, sentence time served; Police Court Commitments showing date, name of prisoner, sentence, felony or misdemeanor charged with.
Arrangement
Chronological order.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Box 19C, Alexandria City Records - Record of Prisoners, 1948-1952.
Box 93, Captain Rufus Dudley Pettit Papers, July 1864-1865. Contains material on the Prince Street Prison during the Civil War.
Separated Material
Two (2) photographs of an unidentified female were transferred to the Photograph Collection: VF (Vertical File): Jail. Photocopies are available in Box 54D, Folder 14.
Index Terms
Jails--Virginia--Alexandria
Contents List
- Jail Register, July 1, 1891-1893 (Box-folder 54:1)
  Alternative form available
  A photocopy of the Register is available for use.
- Jail Register, January 1895-June 1897 (Box 54A)
- Jail Register, November 1903-October 1912 (Box 54A)
- Jail Register, November 1912-December 1922 (Box 54B)
- Jail Register, January 1923-November 1928 (Box 54B)
- Jail Register - City Cases, December 1, 1928-March 31, 1929 (Box-folder 54C:1)
- Jail Register - City Cases, April 1, 1928-July 31, 1929 (Box-folder 54C:2)
- Jail Register - City Cases, August 1, 1929-October 31, 1929 (Box-folder 54C:3)
- Jail Register - City Cases, November 1, 1929-December 31, 1929 (Box-folder 54C:4)
- Jail Register - City Cases, January 1, 1930-March 31, 1930 (Box-folder 54C:5)
- Jail Register - City Cases, April 1, 1930-June 30, 1930 (Box-folder 54C:6)
- Jail Register - City Cases, July 1, 1930-September 30, 1930 (Box-folder 54C:7)
- Jail Register - City Cases, October 1, 1930-December 1, 1930 (Box-folder 54C:8)
- Jail Register - State Cases, December 1, 1928-December 31, 1929 (Box-folder 54C:9)
- Jail Register - State Cases, June 1, 1930-December 31, 1930 (Box-folder 54C:10)
- Jail Register - City Cases, January 1, 1931-March 31, 1931 (Box-folder 54C:11)
- Jail Register - State Cases, June 1, 1931-December 31, 1931 (Box-folder 54C:12)
- Jail Register - City Cases, April 1, 1931-December 31, 1931 (Box-folder 54C:13)
- Jail Register - City Prisoners, January 1, 1932-June 30, 1932 (Box-folder 54C:14)
- Jail Register - State Cases, January 1, 1932-May 31, 1932 (Box-folder 54C:15)
- Commitment for Further Examination, March 15, 1946-December 28, 1946; February 7, 1948-December 17, 1948 (Box-folder 54D:1)
- Police Court Commitment, January 7, 1946-December 12, 1946; January 2, 1948-November 17, 1948 (Box-folder 54D:2)
- Jail Service Certificate, February 15, 1933-April 7, 1933 (Box-folder 54D:3)
- Jail Service Certificate, April 8, 1933-June 3, 1933 (Box-folder 54D:4)
- Jail Service Certificate, July 27, 1933-September 9, 1933 (Box-folder 54D:5)
- Jail Service Certificate, September 9, 1933-October 26, 1933 (Box-folder 54D:6)
- Jail Service Certificate, October 27, 1933-February 11, 1934 (Box-folder 54D:7)
- Jail Service Certificate (blank) (Box-folder 54D:8)
- Jail Service Certificate (blank) (Box-folder 54D:9)
- Court Order, January 10, 1946-December 15, 1948 (Box-folder 54D:10)
- List Supplies Store House City Jail, July 4, (19??) (Box-folder 54D:11)
- Week Menu for Prisoners, n.d. (Box-folder 54D:12)
- Letter from J.J. Mastin, Commissioner of State Board of Welfare, Commonwealth of Virginia, to Alexandria Police Department, May 5, 1925 (Box-folder 54D:13)
- Two (2) photos (copies) of an unidentified female. (Box-folder 54D:14)
- Record of Conduct of Prisoners in Jail, April 10, 1911-October 29, 1922 (Box 54E)
  Shows name of prisoner, date of commitment, length of sentence, resolution of sentence.
- Daily Jail Record, May 1, 1925-May 24, 1926 (Box 54E)
  Indicates number of prisoners each day in jail - male, female, race.